Guide to the Argus Archives Records
Argus Archives Records
1914, 1931-2004 (bulk 1970-1990)
1914 2004
Argus Archives
MC 00338
The Argus Archives Records, 1914-2004 (bulk 1970-1990), contain brochures, catalogs, correspondence, legislation, magazines, memorabilia, monographs, news clippings, pamphlets, photographs, research reports, video, and other materials collected and preserved by Argus Archives in pursuit of its goal to be an information source in humane education and to stop unnecessary or particularly cruel forms of animal testing. With particular focus on collecting material relating to humane organizations in the State of New York, Argus Archives actively assembled information on all areas of interest to the humane movement. The collection expanded to include organizations in all of North America and parts of Europe and Asia. Biographical documents of Dallas Pratt and other material such as article reprints date back to 1914.
The Argus Archives was founded in New York City by Dallas Pratt in 1969. In addition to acting as a data bank to provide facts to other humane groups with which to influence community leaders and legislators, Argus Archives was also dedicated to the efforts of humane education, supporting change at the community level.
205.5 linear feet
North Carolina State University Libraries, Special Collections Research Center
Gift of Animal Welfare Institute, 2004 (Accession no. 2004-0005); some manuscript materials purchased for the NCSU Libraries by various anonymous donors, 2003 (Accession no. 2003-0004).
This collection consists of ten series: 1. Organizational Files2. Animals' Agenda Files3. Betty B. Eilers Files (Moved to Animal Rights Network Records, MC 00351)4. Photographs5. News Clippings6. Theme Files7. Film Literature8. Humane Education Films9. Publications10. Related Items
Dallas Pratt founded the Argus Archives, a privately funded New York foundation, in 1969 to serve the needs of animals by collecting factual and comprehensive information about their mistreatment and conditions which affect their well being, with particular reference to the State of New York. Acting in its primary function as a data bank of information on all areas of interest to the humane movement, its goal was to provide facts to other humane groups with which to influence community leaders and legislators. To accomplish this, Argus Archives assembled information on all aspects of animal welfare and animal mistreatment, performed research, and provided reports and publications such as: Furs and Fashion-Traps and Trapping in 1971 and the revised edition; Traps and Trapping Furs and Fashion in 1977, Unwanted Pets and the Animal Shelter in 1973 as part of a report series. Argus Archives also published works authored by Dallas Pratt, including Painful Experiments on Animals, 1976 and Alternatives to Pain in Experiments on Animals, 1980, for which he won the 1981 Animal Welfare Institute's Schweitzer Medal. In addition, Argus Archives held semi-annual film presentations for the purpose of humane education to an invited audience of humane groups, educators, and the media, after which the guests were asked to write a brief critique of each film.
In a brief autobiography written in 1984, Dallas Pratt reflected about his three careers: twenty-six years practicing psychiatry, twenty-seven years collecting antiques for and helping to finance the American Museum in Britain, and sixteen years active in the prevention of cruelty to animals. This last he referred to as the biggest challenge of all, "this sixteen year effort to make, persuade, beg people to be more imaginative in their dealings with animals. Making information available in depth, writing and publishing books, and the use of films are ways where by my colleagues and I have tried to reach the public"(Box 1, Folder 2). After Dr. Pratt's death on May 20, 1994, at the age of seventy-nine, the Argus Archives became a division of Two Mauds, Inc., a foundation directed by Ron Scott.
Animal Rights Network Records, 1903-2003 (MC 00351)
Animal Welfare Institute Records, 1945-1994 (MC 00344)
Ron Scott Animal Rights Videotape Collection (MC 00339)
The Argus Archives Records document the establishment of the archives and the business functions related to its mission as both a resource for other humane education organizations and in its capacity as a humane education organization. The material collected by the Argus Archives focuses on the daily treatment of animals and characterizes the efforts of humane organizations in North America and parts of Europe and Asia to stop abuse through humane education and legislation. Although the material does not present opposing viewpoints, not all organizations in the collection are humane groups. Material from film studios and auto manufacturers, for example, are also included. In addition, these records do not attempt to document the daily business functions of the organizations represented within the collection, but there are instances where corporate records are present. (Note: Series 3, the Betty B. Eilers Series was removed from this collection and incorporated with additional Betty B. Eilers materials in the Animal Rights Network Records).
The various formats include brochures, bumper stickers, buttons, catalogs, CD-ROMs, coloring-books, correspondence, invitations, legislation, monographs, news clippings, newsletters, pamphlets, programs, posters, petitions, photographs, published articles, regulations, reports, reprints, and a videocassette. Topics include, but are not limited to: vivisection, the use of animals in cinema and other human entertainment, fishing and hunting, environmental impacts on animal habitats, vegetarianism, and companion animals.
Argus Archives; Animal Welfare Institute; Regan Tom; Pratt Dallas; Scott, Ronald; Two Mauds, Inc.; Humane education Film catalogs; Laboratory animals; Meat industry and trade; Social conditions 20th century New York (N.Y.); Clippings; Animals Pictorial works; Humane education; Animal rights activists; Animal rights; Societies, etc. Animal welfare; Animal welfare; Photographs; Social conditions 20th century United States; Animal experimentation; Social conditions 20th century New York (State); Vivisection; Veganism; Vegetarianism
- Organizational Files, 1914, 1932-1994; 1914 1994; 63 linear feet
  Included in the Organizational Files series are records documenting the establishment of the Argus Archives, its collection goals and practices, and materials produced by approximately 800 humane organizations in their efforts to inform the public about the daily abuse of animals in society. Topics include, but are not limited to: vivisection, the use of animals in cinema and other human entertainment, fishing and hunting, environmental impacts on animal habitats, vegetarianism, and companion animals.
  Folders had been created for the following organizations, but the folders were empty when received at NCSU: ARIES - The ARIES NewsletterAVA - American Veterinary AssociationAVHA - Animal Welfare League of Alexandria, Va., Inc.BCS - British Columbia SPCABHG - Bunny Huggers' GazetteCAWD - Canadian-American Wolf DefendersCLAL - Committee for Constructive laboratory LegislationCWD California Wildlife DefendersDOC - Docktor Pet CentersDPA - Defense at ProtectionDRF - Dalmation Research FoundationDSC - Distilled Spirits Council of the U.S., Inc.ECPS - Eur. Com. for Pro. Seals and Other Fur AnimalsEJMH - D. J. Meyer Memorial Hop.FAL - The Friends of All LifeHCB - Children's Hospital of BuffaloHD - Handi-Dogs, Inc.HJ - Jamaica Hospital, N.Y.HSJ - St. Joseph's Hospital, Burbank, Ca.IAWL - Illinois Citizens Welfare LeagueIBM - IBM Data Processing DivisionICR - Imperial Cancer Research FundIFHS - Indiana Federation of Humane SocietiesITTS - International Turtle and Tortoise SocietyLF - Lovelace Foundation for Medical Education and ResearchLFI - Lovelace Foundation, Inhalation Toxicology Research InstituteNIEH - National Institute of Environmental Health SciencesNTA - National Trappers AssociationNYMR - New York State Society for Medical ResearchOTTER - OtterwisePAWP - "Pawprints" - Pound Animal Welfare SocietyPET - Psychologists for the Ethical Treatment of AnimalsPETA - People for the Ethical Treatment of AnimalsPLG - Pet Lovers' Gazette (newspaper)PO - Peoples OaklandSBHM - St. Bartholomew's Hospital Medical College (London)SFCI - Sidney Farber Cancer InstituteSR - Syntex ResearchSTER - Sterling Drug, Inc.TBC - Tobacco Research Council (London)UAD - United Animal DefendersUAM - University of Amsterdam (Netherlands)UAN - Australian National University (Canberra)UBG - Bowling Green State University, OhioUBM - Baylor College of Medicine, HoustonUBPB - Brown University, Psychology Department (Primate Behavior Lab)UBR - Bradley University, Peoria, IL.UCFE - College de France Lab. d'embryologie Exp.UCHE - Columbia University, Harkness Eye InstituteUCI - University of California, IrvineUCMD CMDNG - Rutgers Medical School, UCO - University of ColoradoUCPM - University of Chicago, Pritaker School of MedicineUCSO - University of California - Scripps Institute of OceanographyUCWB - Columbia University, William Black Research BuildingUD - University of DelawareUDM - Duke University Medical CenterUE - Emory UniversityUED - University of Edinburgh (Scotland)UI - University of IowaUIN - University of IndianaUKHS - U.K. Home Office, Commission on Safety of MedicineUKL - K.U.L. (Leuven, Belgium)ULC - Livingston College (New Brunswick, NY)ULF - Lake Forest College, Lake Forest, ILULI - University of Long IslandULM - Louisiana State University Medical CenterUM - University of MarylandUMID - Middlebury College, VermontUMNA - University of Minnesota, College of AgricultureUMG - McGill University (Montreal)UMO - University of MissouriUMS - Michigan State UniversityUMSP - University of Mississippi School of PharmacyUMTP - MIT, Department of PsychologyUNAM - State University of New York, AmherstUNBX - State University of New York, Bronx (Maritime College)UNCA - State University of New York, CantonUNCO - State University of New York, CortlandUND - State University of New York, DelhiUNFA - State University of New York, FarmingdaleUNFR - State University of New York, FredoniaUNG - State University of New York, GenescoUNH - University of New HampshireUNI - Northern Illinois UniversityUNJM - New Jersey Medical SchoolUNN - State University of New York, New PaltzUNNY - State University of New York, New York City (School of Optometry)UNOS - State University of New York, OswegoUNP - State University of New York, PurchaseUNPL - State University of New York, PlattsburghUNPO - State University of New York, PotsdamUNY - State University of New York (SUNY)UPAM - University of Pennsylvania Medical SchoolURU - Rutgers University, Camden, NJUSAA - U.S. Air Force School of Aerospace MedicineUSAW - Walter Reed Army Institute of ResearchUSOS - U.S. Occupational Safety and Health AdministrationUTXA - University of Texas at AustinUTXM - University of Texas Medical School, HoustonUUAM - Union University, Albany Medical CollegeUVCM - Virginia Commonwealth University, Medical CollegeUVM - University of Virginia School of MedicineUVN - Vanderbilt University (Nashville, TN)UWS - Wayne State UniversityUX - Syracuse UniversityUXA - University of Southern AlabamaUXCM - Medical University of South CarolinaUXJ - San Jose State University, CaliforniaUXTO - University of StockholmVHSC - Veterans Administration Hospital, Sepulveda, CAVWH - V.A Hospital, West Haven, Conn.
  Folders in this series are alphabetized by organizational acronym. Each organization file may then contain a number of folders represented by the labeling system P1, P2, P3 etc. Although these labels record accurately the number of folders within a file, they do not uniformly represent the same content. For example, folder P1 may contain correspondence in one file and newsletters in another. In addition, if for preservation purposes it has been determined that one folder was insufficient to hold the material within it, that content has been put into several folders, which has created occurrences where one organization might have six folders labeled P1. Each one of these folders contains the content, in original order, of the folder created by the Argus Archives.
  - AA - Argus Archives: Newsletters, clippings, handwritten notes, published articles, invitation, 1989-1994 (Box 1.001, Folder 1)
    Newsletter - “Supporting the Advancement of Cancer Pain” Guide for Patient and Families, Vol. II no. 1, News clippings - N.Y. Times Personal Health Section “Cancer Pain is beatable but too few know it” by Jane E. Brody “Museum co-founder fills life with 3 careers” by Matt Schudel Program - 36th Film Presentation November. News-clipping - News and Observer Raleigh N.C. Handwritten notes - “contents of my journal page #s 93 and 94 Typed list / Dallas Pratt’s Biography, original and one photocopy, begins with date and place of birth and lists summer and winter trips from 1914 to 1989.
  - AA - Argus Archives: Correspondence, Biographical Information, 1936-1989 (Box 1.001, Folder 2)
    Correspondence - To Oren Root, President of National Association for Mental Health, Subject: Letter of resignation from Dallas Pratt (unsigned). Attached notes from Education Division Products NMHF, and to R. Wechsler, includes biographical and bibliographic information; Who's Who in the East, 20th Edition, Curriculum Vitae, two page biography
  - AA - Argus Archives: Correspondence, Photographs, Newsletter, News clipping, 1985-1991 (Box 1.001, Folder 3)
    HELP TIBET brochure and donation request with return envelope and newsletter.
  - AA - Argus Archives: Correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 1.001, Folder 4)
    Correspondence between Redress Trust and Dallas Pratt.
  - AA - Argus Archives: Material related to dinner parties, 1984-1992 (Box 1.001, Folder 5)
    Personal dinner invitations both sent and received, guest lists, table arrangement, menus including Anti-Slavery Society dinner and Inauguration of the Friends of the Anti-Slavery Society.
  - AA - Argus Archives: Fire preparedness research material, 1983 April 21 (Box 1.001, Folder 6)
    Research for purchase of fire-related equipment: smoke alarms, water jel fire blanket, escape ladder, two news clippings about what to do in fire, one emergency care manual for burns and smoke inhalation "Get low and get out, A Teacher's Guide"
  - AA - Argus Archives: Correspondence, 1986-1992 (Box 1.001, Folder 7)
    Correspondence between Pratt and N.Y.C. Department of Buildings
  - AA - Argus Archives: Papers relating to homeowners insurance, 1986-1992 (Box 1.001, Folder 8)
  - AA - Argus Archives: Handwritten notes, memoranda, administrative records relating to the organization of the archive, 1973 September 27 (Box 1.001, Folder 9)
  - AA - Argus Archives: Handwritten notes, memoranda, administrative records, circa 1969 (Box 1.001, Folder 10)
  - AA - Argus Archives: Research, administrative codes, certificate of merit, prayer card, 1955, circa 1969, 1974 (Box 1.001, Folder 11)
  - AA - Argus Archives: Suggested notational system for Argus Archives documents, circa 1969 (Box 1.001, Folder 12)
  - AA - Argus Archives: Correspondence, administrative, photographic print, 1969-1989 (Box 1.001, Folder 13)
  - AA - Argus Archives: Report, 1971 November (Box 1.002, Folder 1)
    "Furs and Fashion: Traps and Trapping.", Vol 2 no. 2, with notes relating to suggested quotes for "It's a Fact."
  - AA - Argus Archives: Correspondence, 1974 (Box 1.002, Folder 2)
    Correspondence between Martha D. Coe and Dallas Pratt relating to research inquiries with a handwritten note about helping Peter Singer with his book "Animal Liberation."
  - AA - Argus Archives: Monograph, 1976 (Box 1.002, Folder 3)
    Painful Experiments on Animals by Dallas Pratt M.D.
  - AA - Argus Archives: Monograph, Bulletin, 1980 (Box 1.002, Folder 4)
    Alternatives to Pain in Experiments on Animals by Dallas Pratt M.D.
  - AA - Argus Archives: Photographic Prints, 1970s (Box 1.002, Folder 5)
    Depicting speakers at a podium, Barbizon-Plaza.
  - AA - Argus Archives: Reports, 1973 (Box 1.002, Folder 6)
    Argus Archive Report Series No. 4 - "Unwanted Pets and the Animal Shelter"; "The Pet Population Problem in New York State"
  - AA - Argus Archives: Article, 1970s (Box 1.002, Folder 7)
    "Animals in Trouble": a new Information Service
  - AA - Argus Archives: Monograph and notes, 1977 (Box 1.002, Folder 8)
    Traps and Trapping Furs and Fashion revised edition by Jean Stewart
  - AA - Argus Archives: Publishing brochures, 1970s (Box 1.002, Folder 9)
  - AA - Argus Archives: Publishing brochures, 1970s (Box 1.002, Folder 10)
  - AA - Argus Archives: Material relating to copyright, 1972, 1982 (Box 1.002, Folder 11)
  - AA - Argus Archives: Correspondence, 1968-1988 (Box 1.002, Folder 12)
  - AA - Argus Archives: Film reviews in Humane Education, 1982-1984 (Box 1.002, Folder 13)
  - AA - Argus Archives: Journal Entry, Humane education, 1968 April 4, 1970-1977 (Box 1.002, Folder 14)
  - AA - Argus Archives: Humane education, photographic prints, 1968 (Box 1.002, Folder 15)
    Photographs (quantity 2) (5 x 5 b & w) depicting a dead PMU foal
  - AA - Argus Archives: Correspondence, 1968-1970 (Box 1.002, Folder 16)
    A series of letters from and responses to Iris (August) von Muggenthaler.
  - AA - Argus Archives: Correspondence, essay, research, court case, 1973 December 14 (Box 1.003, Folder 1)
  - AA - Argus Archives: Correspondence, interview, speech, articles, and film presentation program, 1981-1988 (Box 1.003, Folder 2)
  - AA - Argus Archives: Correspondence, Typescript, Magazine, 1976-1978 (Box 1.003, Folder 3)
    Correspondence relating to "On Watch at Argus Archive." Typescript of article; "On Watch at Argus Archive." Original copy of Pet News in which article appeared, p. 42-43.
  - AA - Argus Archives: Photographic prints and negatives, 1977-1982 February 12 (Box 1.003, Folder 4)
    Photographs (3, 8 x 10 b & w) used in Pet News article. Photographs (1, 3 and ½ x 5 color) and one contact sheet of 24 images of Dr. Dallas Pratt at special showing of film "KoKo," at 228 E.49th Street, N.Y., N.Y. Pratt is pictured talking with guests, inviting critiques after the film, photo by Richard Clark. One b & w 5 x 7 and one color 3 and ½ x 5 showing audience answering questionnaires, plus five negative strips
  - AA - Argus Archives: Published articles, 1977-1983 (Box 1.003, Folder 5)
    Article from Animal Crackers, The Anti-Cruelty Society; Vol. 3, No. 3. Pratt is featured in the profile section. Article from California Veterinarian, "Research and Testing Can Be Painful, Outmoded, and Unreliable", by Dallas Pratt. Article, from AVAR, "Research Animals Population Statistics" from Dallas Pratt.
  - AA - Argus Archives: Published articles, poster, newsletter, 1985 August, 1988, 1989 April, 1989 October 8 (Box 1.003, Folder 6)
    Newsletter; International Primate Protection League; Vol. 12 No. 2, "Necessary Fuss" by Dallas Pratt. Magazine; The Animals' Voice; Vol. 2 No. 2, "A Man For All Reasons- An Interview with Dallas Pratt by Dr. Tom Regan." Poster; "Triangle Animal Awareness," Ronald Scott pictured. Newsletter article; Focus; "En Route To Harrisburg and Hegins, Pa." by Ron Scott
  - AA - Argus Archives: Bibliography and evaluation, 1989-1990 June 4 (Box 1.003, Folder 7)
    Bibliography of available video footage.
  - AA - Argus Archives: Programs, 1976 May 10-1977 November (Box 1.003, Folder 8)
    Programs of Argus Archives Film Presentation, 7th - 10th.
  - AA - Argus Archives: Programs and invitation, 1979 November-1982 May, 1980 (Box 1.003, Folder 9)
    Programs of Argus Archive Film Presentation, 14th - 19th.- Invitation; "Films for Humane Education"
  - AA - Argus Archives: Programs, 1982 November-1987 May (Box 1.003, Folder 10)
    Programs for Argus Archives Film Presentation, 20th - 29th.
  - AA - Argus Archives: Programs, 1987 November-1992 May (Box 1.003, Folder 11)
    Programs for Argus Archives Film Presentation, 30th - 32nd and 34th - 39th.
  - AA - Argus Archives: Programs, 1992 November-1993 November (Box 1.003, Folder 12)
    Programs for Argus Archive Film Presentation, 40th - 42nd.
  - AA - Argus Archives: Humane Education, 1990 February 22 (Box 1.003, Folder 13)
    Article; book review of "Animal Liberation" by Peter Singer. Memo to Julie explaining, "The prints of African animals are a bequest from Zac Watts who died recently," initialed by Dallas Pratt.
  - AA - Argus Archives: Humane Education, 1968 (Box 1.003, Folder 14)
    The Trump Village Case: "A VICTORY FOR PETS"
  - AA - Argus Archives: Report, undated (Box 1.003, Folder 15)
    "Discrimination against pets in housing."
  - AA - Argus Archives: Report, 1970 August (Box 1.004, Folder 1)
    "Animals in Trouble: Pets in Urban Housing," Vol. 1 No. 1, two copies in manuscript form
  - AA - Argus Archives: Report, 1970 August (Box 1.004, Folder 2)
    "Animals in Trouble: Pets in Urban Housing," Vol. 1 No. 1, two distributed copies
  - AA - Argus Archives: Report, 1970 August (Box 1.004, Folder 3)
    "Animals in Trouble: Pets in Urban Housing," Vol. 1 No. 1, one distributed copy with notes for suggested quotes for: "It's a Fact."
  - AA - Argus Archives: Humane education, 1971 (Box 1.004, Folder 5)
    Alternatives to Pain in Experiments on Animals German Edition Notes-Index to Alternatives to Pain in Experiments on Animals, pages 269 -272-Review: Frame Book Review of Alternatives to Pain in Experiments on Animals. Review: Tages-Anzeiger Book Review of Alternatives to Pain in Experiments on Animals, Alternativen zum Tierversuch empfohlen
  - AA - Argus Archives: Humane education workshop, 1989 September 23 (Box 1.004, Folder 6)
    Medical Experts in the Media - A Media Skills Workshop.
  - AA - Argus Archives: Slides, correspondence, 1986 November 20, 1990 June 10 (Box 1.004, Folder 7)
    Argus Film Show, 10 color Ektachrome slides. Correspondence from Tom Regan to Ron Scott, donation of $200.00. Photograph: "Ron Scott, standing on left wearing green hat" filming at a march on Washington.
  - AA - Argus Archives: Magazine, 1989-1990 (Box 1.004, Folder 8)
    Shelter Sense, Vol. 13, No. 1 "Animals for Humane Education" p. 14.; with accompanying note from Shelter Sense Assistant Editor.
  - AA - Argus Archives: Research, 1990 (Box 1.004, Folder 9)
    NEAVS Application for Fellowship Grant submitted by Patricia Lamb Feurstein.
  - AA - Argus Archives: Research, 1987-1990 (Box 1.004, Folder 10)
    Book Review Newsletter; Spectrum Review Vols. 1 - 11. Published by Georg Feurstein, husband to Patricia Lamb Feurstein. Article in Vol. 9; "Animal Rights and Human Consciousness by Trisha Feurstein.
  - AA - Argus Archives: Correspondence with state agencies relating to the request for copies of state laws and their replies, 1978-1979 (Box 1.0091, Folder 4)
  - AA - Argus Archives: A compilation of varying organizations originally filed under miscellaneous, 1970s-1980s (Box 1.0091, Folder 5)
  - AA - Argus Archives: A compilation of varying organizations originally filed under miscellaneous, 1970s-1980s (Box 1.0092, Folder 1)
  - AA - Argus Archives: Travel, 1992 August 7 (Box 1.0092, Folder 2)
  - AA - Argus Archives: "Library Photocopying and the U.S. Copyright Law of 1976,", 1977 December 29 (Box 1.101, Folder 1)
  - AA - Argus Archives: Reprints of "The Don Juan Myth" by Dallas Pratt, 1960 (Box 1.101, Folder 2)
  - AA - Argus Archives: Monograph, Principles of Archaeological Stratigraphy by Edward C. Harris, 1979 (Box 1.101, Folder 3)
  - AA - Argus Archives: Offprint - "World Archaeology" by Edward C. Harris, 1975 June (Box 1.101, Folder 4)
  - AA - Argus Archives: The Journal of Pastoral Care with article by Dallas Pratt, "Values - Their Dynamics in Behavior and Psychotherapy,", 1955 Winter (Box 1.101, Folder 5)